<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Assume Wisely - Artificial Intelligence]]></title><description><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence and data science programming resources.]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 23:37:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[7x7 Interview Challenge]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Seven interviews in seven days. That's the goal. 
If you've failed at interviewing, it's not your fault. 
Information overload is real and it will keep you from success.
If that's you, it's ok. You are in the right place.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/interview-challenge</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/interview-challenge</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Welcome to the 7x7 Interview Challenge. The next cohort is in January. You can sign up [here](https://7x7interviewchallenge.assumewisely.com). I&apos;m going to take you step by step through a process that is going to line up interviews.

Are you actively looking for their first data science role right now?

If you&apos;ve failed at interviewing, it&apos;s not your fault. There&apos;s a lot of information out there, and it&apos;s confusing.

Information overload is real and it will keep you from success.



It&apos;s ok. 

If you&apos;ve been concerned that you just can&apos;t succeed in data science, I want to put those fears to rest. You can do this. You just need the right guidance.

 

There are huge industries that profit off you thinking that you need

- some fancy degree,
- or to attend the right schools,
- to shackle yourself with debt,
- or know the right people to be successful.


I&apos;m telling you that isn&apos;t the whole story. They have their reasons for wanting you to think that, but it&apos;s just not true. If you&apos;ve ever thought that job applications and the hiring process are set up to weed you out, you&apos;re not wrong.  I&apos;m here today because I care about your success. This is course I wish I had when I was getting started. That is what we are here for. I know you have aspirations
- to change the world for your family
- to make an impact. 

I want to show you how to make that happen.



[![Seven Interviews In Seven Days](./media/ads/interview_challenge_ad.png)](https://7x7interviewchallenge.assumewisely.com)


## The Measuring Stick

When we finish here, you will judge me. Some of you may judge me harshly simply because you have different goals than I do. I don&apos;t want you leave you wondering, is this for me?

My goal for this presentation is to help four types of people:

- recent college grads &amp; boot-campers
- experienced data people (DBAs, data engineers, data analysts)
- parents returning to work
- and candidates with diverse backgrounds

For those with little to no experience, I&apos;m helping you to break into the space. This course was designed with you in mind.

For more experienced job seekers, DBAs, data engineers, etc. When I first developed this course it was with recent college grads and candidates with little to no experience in mind. But, I&apos;m meeting solid candidates with a wealth of experience who are having trouble translating that experience into the next stage of their career. I got you too.

## Interview Hacking

My goal is to get you to believe that interview hacking is the first domino of a series. When you master this, everything else will fall into place. You will get your first data science role, and every role after.

 ”hacking” isn&apos;t just for coders. In fact, the simple mindset of a hacker can help you reboot your career and reach your potential without wasting more time.

Good?

If you&apos;re ready, Say I&apos;m ready. And [click here](https://7x7interviewchallenge.assumewisely.com) to get started.

[![Seven Interviews In Seven Days](./media/ads/interview_challenge_ad.png)](https://7x7interviewchallenge.assumewisely.com)
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hume’s Turkey: A Tale of Thanksgiving.]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Hume's turkey lives on a farm. From this turkey's perspective life is good. Of course, there are bad days . . .
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/humes-turkey</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/humes-turkey</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Like most turkeys, Hume&apos;s turkey lives on a farm. From this turkey&apos;s perspective life is good. Of course, there are bad days: the weather might turn cold, the older turkeys might box him out from the best seed and grass, a fox might get into the coupe. Overall life is good because of the farmer. The farmer loves his turkey.

The farmer keeps the coup, which protects the turkey from the weather. The farmer defends the turkey from the fox. The farmer makes sure the turkey gets enough to eat. The turkey is happy because the farmer loves him.

The turkey lives his life, without concern for the future. The turkey has no way of knowing, based on experience, that he will soon be dinner.

We put ourselves at risk when looking to the past as a predictor of what will be. That is the problem with knowledge gained from induction, that is the turkey&apos;s dilemma. 

Bertrand Russell is credited with the idea of the turkey&apos;s dillema in highlighting the holes in David Humes arguments about knowledge gained by induction.

Adapted from The Black Swan, by Nassim Taleb.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to Become A Data Scientist i Strategy Guide]]></title><description><![CDATA[
A Data Scientist I is responsible for analyzing and interpreting complex data sets to help businesses make informed decisions. This role involves designing experiments and creating predictive models. Often the primary value add for the business is communicating data-driven insights to stakeholders.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/data-scientist-i</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/data-scientist-i</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>As the world becomes increasingly data-driven, companies are seeking skilled professionals who can turn complex data sets into actionable insights. There is a pressing demand for &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; positions, but it&apos;s a misconception to think of it as an entry-level position. The role of a &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; requires a combination of skills in statistics, business, and development that are built up through experience and education.

## What is a &quot;Data Scientist I&quot;?

A &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; is responsible for analyzing and interpreting complex data sets to help businesses make informed decisions. This role involves designing experiments and creating predictive models. Often the primary value add for the business is communicating data-driven insights to stakeholders. A &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; may work on a variety of projects, including customer behavior analysis, risk modeling, and optimization.

## Skills Needed for the Role of a &quot;Data Scientist I&quot;

To be successful in the role of a &quot;Data Scientist I,&quot; candidates must possess a combination of skills in statistics, business, and development. These skills are crucial in performing tasks such as data cleaning and manipulation, creating visualizations, and building predictive models.

**Statistics:** A solid foundation in statistics is a must-have for a &quot;Data Scientist I.&quot; The role requires the ability to apply statistical concepts such as regression analysis, hypothesis testing, and clustering to large data sets. A &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; should be comfortable using statistical software such as ScikitLearn and TensorFlow to build models.

**Business:** A &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; needs to have a strong understanding of the business they are working in. This means being able to identify key business metrics and use data to help drive decision-making. They should be able to communicate complex data insights to stakeholders in a way that is understandable and actionable. 

**Development:** A &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; should have some programming experience, particularly in languages such as SQL, Python and Javascript. This will enable them to manipulate data, build models, and create visualizations efficiently. Familiarity with big data technologies such as Hadoop and Spark is also a plus.

## Practical Tips for Gaining Experience

While there are formal education options for those interested in pursuing a career as a &quot;Data Scientist I,&quot; relevant experience is paramount. Candidates should have experience in one or all of the required skills to qualify for the role. This can be gained through internships, personal projects, or even through online courses.

[![Tired of Hearing You Need More Experience](./media/ads/sad_chick.png)](http://experiencebook.assumewisely.com)

## Relevant Experience is Paramount

If you want to gain experience in statistics, you can take applied statistics courses as well as engage in competitions. Nate Silver&apos;s &quot;The Signal and the Noise&quot; is a must read. In addition, you can find other suggestions in my strategy blueprint, &quot;[Experience: The Fastest Way To Actually Get Hired As A Data Scientist.](https://experiencebook.assumewisely.com)&quot;

Whatever your current role, there are business problems you can solve with data. For instance, even something as simple as optimizing the time it takes to complete a task can be solved with data. If you are a customer service representative, analyzing call transcripts by topic and sentiment can help identify areas where support can be improved or should be prioritized. As an operations manager, examining throughput can help identify bottlenecks and inefficiencies that can be addressed to reduce costs. Whatever you do, volunteer for projects that involve analyzing data related to marketing, sales, or customer behavior. 

To gain technical skills in data analysis and manipulation, look no further than Google&apos;s Big Query. Big Query provides access to vast public data sets, free of charge. Focus on learning SQL. Begin exploring and analyzing data that piques your interest. With Big Query has a free tier. Combined with access to public data, the possibilities for gaining practical data analysis experience are endless!

## Career Path and Opportunities

A &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; can expect to have a lucrative and rewarding career. The role has excellent earning potential and job growth prospects. With experience, a &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; can move up the ladder to roles such as &quot;Data Scientist II,&quot; &quot;Data Science Manager,&quot; or &quot;Chief Data Officer.&quot;

## Challenges in the Job Market

The job market for &quot;Data Scientist I&quot; positions is highly competitive. As the demand for data professionals grows, so does the number of candidates entering the field. It&apos;s essential for job seekers to have the right mix of skills and experience to stand out in a crowded job market. Relevant experience is crucial. Practical tips are available through my my strategy blueprint, [Experience: The Fastest Way To Actually Get Hired As A Data Scientist.](https://experiencebook.assumewisely.com)

This blueprint is the guide I wish I had when I first started out. In it i share how i overcame my own inexperience.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Counterfactual Analysis]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Counterfactual analysis can be used to determine the lift of a campaign or ad. 
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/counterfactual-analysis</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/counterfactual-analysis</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>How would things be different if something hadn&apos;t happened? This is what counterfactual analysis looks at. For example, we can look at how sales change as a result of a new marketing campaign and attribute the incremental lift in sales due to the campaign. By doing this, we can understand what portion of sales is a result of the campaign, and which would have happened anyway. Counterfactual analysis can be done in addition to traditional lift analysis or when traditional lift analysis is not possible.

To figure out what would have happened without the campaign, break your audience into two groups. The first group sees the ad. The second group is similar to the first group, but doesn&apos;t see the ad.

The results from this second control group allow us to see what would have happened with our test group had they not seen the ad.

Counterfactual impact evaluation methods encompass double difference analysis (or difference-in-difference), randomized selection of subjects, propensity score matching and instrumental variable analysis. It is also possible to combine methods. For example, propensity score matching can be used to create treatment and control groups, while double difference analysis can be employed to evaluate the impact of the treatment.

## Double Difference Analysis
Double difference analysis compares treatment and control groups at different time periods. The first step is to look at the difference between the groups. The second step is to look at the difference over time between the groups.

Double difference analysis takes into account that there are some invisible characteristics that account for differences between the treatment and control groups. If these characteristics do not change over time, their impact can be eliminated by comparing both groups before and after the treatment.

Double difference means that two kinds of differences are assessed. Firstly, the difference in time (before and after the intervention), and secondly, the difference between individuals who were subjected to the intervention and those who were not.

Let&apos;s look at how to analyze the average number of sales per day as an example. Assume that an intervention is applied to the treatment group, they see an ad. This will cause a change in time (“before-after”). We can measure much this treatment changes things by subtracting the change in average number of sales per day for the control group from the change in average number of sales per day for the treatment group. This will give us a double difference estimator (treatment’s impact estimate).

Double difference analysis is based on the idea that, if there was no treatment, the average number of sales per day in the treatment group would be the same as the average number of sales per day in the control group. The counterfactual situation is what would have happened if there was no treatment.

## Double Difference Regression
Double difference regression helps to see if the impact is statistically significant. It also helps to take into account the influence of additional periodic or structural factors.

We can develop this regression model:

Yi,t = a + b1*Ti + b2*Pt + b3*Ti*Pt + ԑi,t

where:

**Yi** is the outcome of a sale in a particular period. This can be measured by the number of sales.

**Ti** is a variable that has two possible values: 1, if a product participated in the treatment, and 0, if a product did not participate in the treatment.

**Pt** is a variable that can have two different values. The first value, 0, reflects the time period before the intervention happened. The second value, 1, reflects the time period after the intervention happened.

**Ti*Pt** is the outcome of the two previous variables which acquires value 1 only when the outcome of the product that received the treatment, in the period after the treatment, is taken into account.

**ԑi,t** is an error of the regression.

**a, b1, b2, b3** are parameters of the regression that are under evaluation.

**a** reflects the average outcome (sale) of the product which did not participate in the treatment, in the period before receiving the treatment;

**b1** reflects the initial difference between the treatment and control groups;

**b2** reflects the difference in the outcomes (e.g. sales) of the products that did not participate in the treatment between periods;

**b3** reflects an impact estimate.

The significance of the parameters is evaluated at the same time. For example, if the parameter that reflects the impact estimate is not statistically significant, then it is important to be careful about saying that the assistance definitely had an impact.

**TLDR:** Counterfactual analysis can be used to determine the lift of a campaign or ad. Counterfactual analysis is a method used to determine the difference in outcomes between groups that saw an ad and groups that did not. This analysis takes into account that there are some invisible characteristics that account for differences between groups. If these characteristics do not change over time, their impact can be eliminated by comparing both groups before and after the test group sees the ad.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[here be dragons]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Attempts at controlling extreme risk should come with a warning, here be dragons.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/here-be-dragons</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/here-be-dragons</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
Here be dragons. This phrase was often used by sailors to warn others of the dangers that lay ahead. They would put this phrase on maps to let other sailors know that they were entering uncharted territory, where there were many unknown risks. The same could be said for businesses that try to control their extreme risk. While it is certainly a good idea to take measures to minimize risk, it should come with a similar warning: here be dragons. Controlling extreme risk can be a dangerous game, and should not be taken lightly.

So what does it mean to &quot;control&quot; extreme risk? In business, this can take many forms, from insurance to hedging to diversification. It is important for businesses to understand the different types of risk control available to them, and how each one works. Different types of risk control will work better in different situations, so it is important to tailor the approach to the specific risks faced by the business. Taking a one-size-fits-all approach is usually not effective, and can often do more harm than good.

</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Software Development for DataScientists]]></title><description><![CDATA[
As a data scientist you are probably familiar with coding. But what happens after you build your model. You can't ship a python notebook.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/data-science-programming</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/data-science-programming</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>   
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Working with Messy Data]]></title><description><![CDATA[
This week I spent some time thinking about what data I want in my data warehouse.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/working-with-messy-data</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/working-with-messy-data</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>This week I spent some time thinking about what data I want in my data warehouse. A big piece of what I want is a birds eye view of what my social networks are talking about. I’d like to see a pie chart with the percent of the conversation related to sports, news, politics, Netflix, or just life in general. I’d like to be able to drill down on those conversations where I might add my two cents. I’ve tried listening on social media with Hootsuite and I didn’t get very far. I wasted a lot of time. For now, my first data warehouse is going to focus on social media.

That requires using APIs, web scraping, and NLP (natural language processing) for starters.

Also, this week at work I started a data mining project which involves NLP.

Time to dust off my NLP essentials course. I thought my first real python based project would be similar to the Titanic dataset i worked with. Oh well. There goes that.

## NLP Essentials

Natural Language Processing deals with data that isn&apos;t necessarily in neat columns and rows: like email, reviews, social media posts, etc. You need to be able to parse through the tags and html. 

~~Below is some code that I want to hold onto for later. I&apos;ve tried several strategies for posting my notebook code into wordpress. This is my first attempt. It&apos;s not pretty. It&apos;s an image that links out to a Kaggle Kernals. You can fork it there.~~

Small Edit, I am just [linking out to Kaggle](https://www.kaggle.com/assumewisely/nlp-working-with-messy-data).</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Perception VS Reality]]></title><description><![CDATA[ That is because perceptions are hard to change. Perceptions are like averages in that respect. It doesn't matter . . . ]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/perception-vs-reality</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/perception-vs-reality</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>I have two colleagues who have busted their behinds in the last few months to improve on areas where they were infamously bad. But if you asked around (like a survey) who is the worst? Their names are still at the top of the list!

That is because perceptions are hard to change. Perceptions are like averages in that respect. It doesn&apos;t matter how much improvement there is, all the front end poor performance is baked in. If you want to see the trends, you are better served with a moving average.
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Moral Roots of Liberals & Conservatives]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Watch this video first! You are going to have a hard time with this blog if you don't.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/moral-roots-of-liberals-and-conservatives</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/moral-roots-of-liberals-and-conservatives</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>You are going to have a hard time with this blog if you don&apos;t watch this video. Watch it.

[![Gatsby &amp; TailwindCSS](https://img.youtube.com/vi/8SOQduoLgRw/hqdefault.jpg)](https://www.ted.com/talks/jonathan_haidt_the_moral_roots_of_liberals_and_conservatives)

I am writing this as I watch the video for maybe the fourth or fifth time. I take issue with this first quote:

&quot;Open individuals have an affinity for liberal, progressive, left-wing political views, whereas closed individuals prefer conservative, traditional, right-wing views.&quot; (McCrae, 1996).

That is hard for me accept. I like Applebee&apos;s. And yeah, I saw David&apos;s wiener before I appreciated his abs. So, no I don&apos;t want to eat at Chez-anything but does that mean I can&apos;t appreciate a &quot;global community .... welcoming people from every discipline and culture who ... seek a deeper understanding of the world, and [who] hope to turn that understanding into a better future for us all.&quot; (Ted, 2008)

I love TED. And **AND** I know a lot of conservatives who do too. As a matter of fact, a very right wing conservative shared this video with me. So? What about that? Well, as hard as it is to accept the &quot;closed&quot; label, I choose to (1) accept it&apos;s a real perception and (2) keep an open mind and awareness about that.

## Take the red pill, stay in Wonderland, and I’ll show you how deep the rabbit hole goes.

I love how he ties in the Matrix. First, I just love that movie. Second, he challenges this self-professed liberal audience to make a choice: stay in their blue liberal moral matrix or, swallow the red (republican) pill. I love how he uses the colors to tie politics in with the movie. But in this case the red pill is an invitation to think more . . . conservative. He is simultaneously linking and juxtaposing ideas. Very creative.

## The 5 Foundations of Morality

This is the core of the video. His research identifies how these five channels of morality play out in liberals and conservatives:

- Harm / Care
- Fairness / Reciprocity
- InGroup / Loyalty / Tribes
- Authority / Respect
- Purity / Sanctity

If you don’t already know where you stand, you can take the survey here, [www.YourMorals.org](http://www.yourmorals.org/). Liberals put a higher value on Harm/Fairness. Conservatives put slightly less value on Harm/Fairness but, they put equal weight into all five areas: harm, fairness, InGroup, Authority, and Purity. Liberals discount these last three significantly compared to conservatives. You could say that liberals have a two-channel morality while conservatives have a five-channel.

In our current context loyalty and tribalism gets a bad rap. I really appreciate the value he illustrates that comes from our ability to form groups and sub-groups.

The great conservative insight is that order is precious and it is really easy to lose.

## Can you handle the truth?

Liberals and conservatives both have something to contribute. According to Jonathan Hait, they form a balance on change VS stability. Yin &amp; Yang don&apos;t hate each other. Once we understand this, then the path is open to leave our moral matrix.

&gt; If you want the truth to stand clear before you. Never be for or against. The struggle between &quot;for&quot; and &quot;against&quot; is the mind&apos;s worst disease. ~ Sent-ts&apos;an 700 CE

With that quote in mind, I’d really like to hear what you think. According to Jonathan Hait, liberals and conservatives form a balance on change VS stability. Do you agree? I don’t.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Insolvency Statistics in Canada]]></title><description><![CDATA[
The goal of this visualization is less to present a specific narrative and more to provide a tool that gives a decision maker or interested person the ability to look into the data themselves.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/insolvency-statistics-in-canada</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/insolvency-statistics-in-canada</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Access the [full TABLEAU Data Visualization](https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/rho.lall/viz/InsolvencyStatisticsinCanada/InsolvencyStatisticsinCanada)

The goal of this visualization is less to present a specific narrative and more to provide a tool that gives a decision maker or interested person the ability to look into the data themselves.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A look At the Fundamental Premise of The Book of Mormon Musical]]></title><description><![CDATA[
I was interested in the churches role and influence in Africa so i looked up some numbers. Just the facts; no song and dance.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/book-of-mormon-musical-fundamental-premise</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/book-of-mormon-musical-fundamental-premise</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
A non-LDS friend of mine has been listening to the Book of Mormon musical on Pandora. That sparked some curiosity this week and I decided to write a reboot of a post I published . . . . a long time ago. #preIPHONE 

The Book of Mormon Musical is about a Mormon missionary called to serve in Uganda. Of course he doesn&apos;t know Uganda is in Africa because he is a religious character in American media. In America people of faith are portrayed as one of two stereotypes: (1) uneducated &amp; naive, or (2) bat-shit crazy. In Africa he is forced to confront the harsh realities of life. This experience reveals his religious dogma as insufficient at best.

The premise is that a faith based life is too simple and naive to offer real help for the complex realities of life.​

Curiosity piqued. Just what does the church do in Africa? I looked up some numbers. Just the facts; no song and dance.

## Number of Beneficiaries of Humanitarian Aid (2003 – 2010)
&lt;br/&gt;

| Immunizations (with other organizations)      || 42,465,500    |
| --------------------------------------------- |--| ----------- |
| Clean Water                                   ||  3,953,601    |
| Vision Care                                   ||  3,953,601    |
| Neonatal Resuscitation Training               ||     53,130    |
| Wheelchairs                                   ||     37,853    |
| Food Production/Nutrition                     ||      1,000    |
| Other health initiatives total                ||        100    |
| **Total beneficiaries**                       || **46,644,893** |

## Africa Church Statistics
&lt;br/&gt;

| Converts (1/1/10 – 9/30/10)    || 16,198   |
| --------------------------------------------- |--| ----------- |
| Stakes and Districts  || 104   |
| Wards and Branches  || 961 |
| Missions   || 18   |
| Temples   || 3  |
| **Total Church Membership**                       ||     **318,947**   |

I don&apos;t know if you have ever seen someone receive a wheelchair for the first time. I&apos;ve seen a woman drag herself across the dirt floor to climb into her first wheel chair. 

It was transformative. She literally became a person in front of me. And it shames me to admit I couldn&apos;t see her until that point.


(Unfortunatly the original video has been replaced)

[![Latter-day Saint Charities Wheelchair Program](https://img.youtube.com/vi/EwpDz4rZC8I/hqdefault.jpg)](https://youtu.be/EwpDz4rZC8I)

Looking at the facts, it looks like the church is doing a lot. And judging by the growth from 2010 to now, it looks like the message resonates.

I&apos;m not hating on the musical. I haven&apos;t seen it. I&apos;m listening to the soundtrack on Spotify. So far it&apos;s been really funny . . . and offensive. But still really funny. You know what they say? The book is always better.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Job of a DataScientist: Separating Signal from Noise. Machine Learning Under the Hood]]></title><description><![CDATA[
The job of a datascientist is to separate signal from noise. Signal represents valuable consistent relationships that we want to learn. Noise is the random correlations and stuff that will not occur again in the future.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/job-of-data-scientist</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/job-of-data-scientist</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>All data is a combination of signal and noise. Signal represents valuable consistent relationships that we want to learn. Noise is the random correlations and stuff that will not occur again in the future. The combination of signal and noise takes on familiar patterns or shapes that we can use to build a model.

Models can consider varying degrees of signal and noise. On end of the spectrum is the non-model which disregards signal &amp; noise. Consider this common upsell question.

“Would you like fries with that?” This approach requires no model. It disregards signal and noise, rigidly canvassing everyone regardless of who they are or what they ordered:

“I’ll have a salad, hold the dressing. And a bottled water.”

“Would you like fries with that?”

“Carbs? Uh, no thank you.”

On the other end of the spectrum are flexible solutions that consider signal and noise. The predictions gathered are influenced by every piece of data, including outliers which can (and do) skew outcomes. These solutions can be more damaging than using no model at all. Such models lose predictive ability for new data because they are too tightly bound to their original training data. This is called overfitting.

This post is a continuation of my last post where I went over [what is the difference between machine learning and data science](/thoughts/whats-the-difference-between-business-intelligence-and-business-analytics). This post goes a step further to talk about how we use machine learning to separate signal from the noise. There are many machine learning algorithms. Think of them as tools in a tool box. Data scientists use these pre-built algorithms to tease models from their data sets.

A handful of these tools are based on classical statistical methods which makes them easy to interpret. If the model is being used to aid a human to make decisions it’s a good idea to develop the model with these classical methods:

- Linear regression
- Logistic regression
- K-means classification
- K-nearest neighbors
- Hierarchical clustering
- Naive Bayes

There are more options If there is no human involvement in the decision process; think of Netflix making a recommendation, no one reviews the recommendation before you get it. If there is no human element or if there is a high tolerance for opaque black box methods there is an additional group of modern machine learning algorithms:

- Random Forest
- LASSO
- Hidden Markov Models
- Support Vector Regression
- Artificial Neural Networks
- Apriori Algorithms

Discussing each of these is outside the scope of this post. But if you are interested in learning more, make sure to subscribe to my email list for data savvy professionals and get a copy of “Bull Doze Thru Bull.”

**Take away.** If you are evaluating a machine learning project a great question is to ask about the algorithms that were used. LASSO &amp; Random Forest are as close to out of the box all purpose tools as you will find so they are quite common. The classical methods are a conservative choice. The modern machine learning methods are really black box solutions which means they probably tried all of them and went with the tool that performed the best in testing.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Naked Economics Chapter 8 Summary: The Power of Organized Interest]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Naked Economics Chapter 8 Summary: Boiled down to a simple idea, the tail effectively wags the dog.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-8-summary</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-8-summary</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
The “economics of regulation” put simply in Naked Economics Chapter 8 is that the whole (large group) subsidizes the small group(s) because the system rewards self interested politicians who cater to (self interested) organized interest. Remember, large subsidizes small; In this Naked Economics Chapter 8 Summary i&apos;ll cover five contexts he identifies: The (1) analogy of a Christmas tree is an easy visual aid to understand why omnibus spending packages get passed. A counter intuitive context comes from George Stigler, who shows (2) businesses benefit from regulation. He provides a cautionary tale about (3) China’s historical protectionism. He shows how (4) the WTO and Fast Track Authority is used to curtail bad behavior. He concludes sharing (5) an anecdote that exposes our own hypocrisy in the role we play.

## THE MOHAIR ADVANTAGE

We are talking about pork, you need to know what that is. The poster child for pork-barrel legislation is a 40 year subsidy paid out to mohair farmers to ensure the U.S. military supply of yarn to make uniforms. The subsidy was created in 1955. Five years later the military switched to synthetic fibers. The subsidy remained for the next 35 years until public outcry forced it to end in 1995. It made its way back into the budget in 2008.


## NAKED ECONOMICS CHAPTER 8: ​ECONOMICS OF REGULATION

Why did the mohair subsidy come back? It’s asinine. The economics of regulation is a simple model (tool) to help you think about organized interest group politics. Gary Becker, an economist, says it pays to be small. All else equal, small, well organized groups are more successful in the political process. It is easier for the countless masses to pay a few extra cents in taxes to benefit a relative few. Those few are highly motivated to protect that benefit, whereas the general population is largely unaware. As a result, “the democratic process will always favor small, well organized groups at the expense of large diffuse groups (p. 147 of Naked Economics Chapter 8).” In the case of ethanol, a $7 billion tax subsidy is gifted to a small group of farmers, less than 2% of the population. Meanwhile, the cost is spread over the remaining 98%, putting ethanol somewhere below good oral hygiene on our list of concerns. To put that into context for you, this subsidy amounts to $2 a month for every American.
In countries where farming makes up a small fraction of the population, American and Europe, there are subsidies for agriculture. In countries where the farming population is relatively large, China and India, the subsides go the other way, forcing farmers to sell at below market prices. In both cases, the large group, largely unaware, subsidizes the smaller highly motivated group. In politics, the tail wags the dog.

## OH CHRISTMAS TREE: MODELING THE POLITICAL RESPONSE TO ORGANIZED INTEREST.

The process that generated cash payments to mohair farmers is alive and well. This year during Utah’s GOP Convention, senate hopefuls took turns vowing that they would not sign omnibus spending bills. Which means very little in Iowa. The benefits from ethanol subsidies are debatable but it works wonders in Iowa campaigns. The ethanol subsidy puts money in the pockets of Iowa farmers it’s a key issue for them. These omnibus spending bills are like a christmas tree. Each legislator from the house and senate can hang an ornament or two. Each has their constituency to answer to and these spending initiatives go a long way to grease the wheels of those relationships.


## DEATH BY 1,000 SUBSIDIES?

In practice each ornament is called an earmark. Earmarks direct federal money to local projects in the member’s district. 
Each ornament on the tree is insignificant, but taken together they are significant. 
On principle, government should not be in the business of providing incentives for people to do things that would not otherwise make sense. 
The Council for Citizens Against Government Waste identified [$6.8 Billion of pork legislation in the 2017 budget](https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/post-politics/wp/2017/07/19/pork-barrel-spending-on-the-rise-in-congress-watchdog-group-says/?noredirect=on)
. If this was listed out as a line item on the 2017 budget, it would fall between water resources (7.5M) and recreational and sporting services(3.9M). 
 
Pork spending cost my family $80 last year.  We spent $252 on Netflix and Hulu. We spent $7,300 on healthcare.

Where would you look to tighten up this budget?

## BUSINESSES BENEFIT FROM REGULATION

George Stigler of the University of Chicago, 1982 nobel prize winner shows that firms and industries often benefit from regulation. They can create regulation to help themselves or hobble competitors. In illinois the state requires barbers and manicurists to be licensed, but not electricians. Why? Interest groups.
Occupational licensure is a result of special interest groups desire to set up barriers to entry for other seeking to enter the occupation: “The best predictor of whether or not a professional is licensed in Illinois is the size and budget of its professional associations.” Take for example, teacher certification and the teacher’s union. The union is always strongly in favor of teacher certification that enforces rigorous testing and scrutiny for teachers. However, that same policy exempts existing teachers from needing to recertify. This is illogical at best, even disingenuous. If doing certain things is necessary in order to teach, then presumably anyone standing at the front of a classroom should have to do them. The real motive for the licensure is to create a barrier to entry in the teaching profession.  This is good for existing teachers but, not for the education market.
Capitalism is a process of incessantly destroying the old. That may be good for the world; it’s bad for the businesses that make up the “old”. The legislative process helps those who help themselves. Groups under siege from competition can seek, trade protection, bailouts, tax considerations, patents, and other special treatment. There is a crucial distinction between using political process to build safety nets for those harmed by creative destruction and using the process to stop that creative destruction in the first place.

## PROTECTIONISM: A CAUTIONARY EXAMPLE FROM CHINA

Fifteenth century China, 500 years ago, was a far more technologically advanced than the west. China had better science, farming, engineering and medicine. The chinese were using iron 1500 years before Europe (think middle ages). That’s 200 B.C. They were far ahead of the curve.
Where did the industrial revolution happen? Not China. Chinese elites valued stability over progress. They didn’t have the stomach for the wrenching societal changes that made the industrial revolution happen. They banned sea voyaging for trade. They effectively choked off the economic development and discovery that comes from trade.
​
## WTO AND FAST TRACK AUTHORITY

When negotiating international trade deals the president can seek “fast track authority”. This limits congress&apos;s ability to ratify the agreement to a strict up or down vote.  The normal process that allows for amendments (and pork) which can exempt (and protect) certain industries. A trade deal with a few loopholes for every district defeats the purpose. The World Trade Organization uses the same process on the world stage. Each nation has domestic interest groups vying for protection and or benefits. The WTO makes free trade politically manageable by creating a standard that countries must abide by to join: open markets, eliminating subsidies, phasing out tariffs, etc. To have access to the markets of existing members each nation has to agree to the standard. Each of these tools exists as a counter balance to the power that special interests can invoke on politicians at the expense of the general public.
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why Your Salary Will Always Be Below Average]]></title><description><![CDATA[
There are two issues with this number. First you will run into trouble if you look for averages where there aren't any.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/why-your-salary-will-always-be-below-average</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/why-your-salary-will-always-be-below-average</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Have you been on glassdoor lately? Maybe you’ve tried the Payscale salary calculator? Is your take home pay below average? Chances are it is. Use the calculator below and find out.

It’s ok . . . i’ll wait.

Did you check it out? Is that surprising? Before you start planning how to bring this up with your boss you might want to take a second look at that number. I&apos;ll explain.


## Income follows a power law distribution.

There are two issues with this number. First you will run into trouble if you look for averages where there aren&apos;t any. Income follows a power law distribution.

What’s that?

If you have heard of Pareto’s 80/20 rule, that is a power distribution. For income, 80% of the income is earned by 20% of people. Don’t take that literally. 

If we plot out income you would see a small number of people earn a disproportionately larger amount of money relative to everyone else. 

If you try to take the average of a set of incomes (any power distribution) your average will wildly misrepresent the truth. It&apos;s going to underestimate a small number of people, and overestimate the majority. The average makes it seem seem like higher incomes are more common than they are in actuality. Case and point:

Bill Gates walks into a bar and everyone inside becomes a millionaire . . .
 . . . on average.

So when you or someone else pulls up a report on glassdoor and circles the average salary, it is likely not telling the whole story.

But. You might ask, what if Bill Gates doesn’t walk into the bar? What if in this bar we only have locals who all work the same job. I like where your head&apos;s at. You might be onto something. But no, you’re not.

Income follows a power distribution even on a localized scale, it&apos;s just less noticeable. Let&apos;s look at SaaS Implementation Consultants in Provo, UT. The average is $50,800. But look at the range. The low is $39K and the high is $78K. There are a few highly paid individuals driving the average up but most consultants probably earn less than 50K. In full disclosure I don’t know. But the point is neither do you.

The average is not representative of this sample. Let alone the salaries that were not reported.

Implementation consultant earn $50,800  in Provo, UT are on average. 

Average is not the same as usual and customary.

Here is the second issue. What do you think of when I say average? When we talk averages, most people assume it&apos;s a mean. Most people would agree that average and mean are synonymous. That is not the case. An average doesn&apos;t have to be a mean. You can google the definition: a number expressing the central or typical value in a set of data, in particular:

the mode, median, or mean. 

When you read about an average, you could be reading about one of three different measurements. It&apos;s easy to be mislead. The government reports median income. Median is the middle number: 50% earn above median, 50% below. But what if I want to know what salary is usual and customary? What do most people make? This is the mode. If you want to get a sense of where the long tail on the power law distribution falls, the mode would work best. It will tell you what the most common salary is. That could be useful.

The lesson:
Don’t hang your hat on average salary. First, averages don’t fit the data very well. You can take the average, that doesn’t mean you should. Second, when you see an average take steps to learn what kind of average it is. Personally, I find the bookends, the high and low values of a range, to be more useful.

Do you want to learn more? If you a SaaS professional that struggles with aligning your team &amp; getting to the truth then you have come to the right place. Find out how to use averages, bookends, and other KIPs to make better use of your data so you can . . .</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[I Hate Averages.]]></title><description><![CDATA[ Hate is a strong word. But I do hate seeing averages used as KPIs. The problem is . . . ]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/averages</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/averages</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
You Should Too.
 
Hate is a strong word. But I do hate seeing averages used as KPIs. The problem is they are so prevalent. The only practice more prevalent is reporting on raw totals: We did this much in sales, we worked this many hours, etc. etc. (See my Key Performance Indicators PDF for a set of great examples.) Averages are terrible:

One. There are better KPIs that communicate more meaningful information.

Two. You can be taken advantage of when you rely on averages.

**Did I Tell You About The Time I Dated A Model?**

I asked for her number. She was clearly out of my league and she let me know it. I responded that she was acting like a ten when she was clearly a seven. She agreed! Then she started in on herself about how she needed a nose job.

Her error? She only compares herself to other models (not all women). She blew her nose out of proportion. Her view of the world was distorted and I took advantage. I got her number.
Don’t be taken advantage of. There are better options.

**Why Averages Perform Below Average In Your KPIs.**

Out of a group of two-hundred KPIs, I have researched the seven top KPIs for Professional Service firms. None of the seven are from taking averages. Six of them are ratios (and the seventh can be). Isn’t that interesting. So what is so great about ratios?

- Ratios reveal trends and make large numbers easier to digest.
- Ratios provide indicators of organizational performance.
- Ratios allow me to compare apples to oranges.
 

**Three Keys To Understand And Use Ratios.**

First, ratios can be confusing because we were never taught to use ratios in a professional setting. We learned basic fractions. A half or a quarter is an intuitive number. I know what that looks like. I can imagine a pie which gives a fraction meaning. But if a ratio comes out to be 1.09, that is not intuitive. Is it 109%? 92%? Or something else all together?

Second, not every ratio is great. But the great ones compare two opposing metrics. Let’s look at one of my top seven Professional Services KPIs. Revenue Per Employee. If you are in business then revenue is a positive. More revenue is better. More people isn’t necessarily better. This ratio reflects the sensitivity between these two metrics. More revenue will drive the ratio up. More employees will drive it down. More employees will only drive the ratio up if synergies increase revenue at a greater rate. This ratio simplifies the relationship between revenue and employees down to a number. It also lets me compare two companies that are drastically different in terms of size and revenue.

Third. When I first started learning KPIs I spent a lot of time memorizing definitions. I tried to wrap my head around them. It was hard. I re-learned grade school fractions on Khan Academy because I thought it would help. It didn’t. The memorization didn’t either. For every new KPI I had to memorize a new definition. Don’t waste time memorizing definitions!
There is a better way.

**Next time . . . **

In my next blog I am going to teach you a very simple visual aid that has helped me break down ratios so I don’t have to memorize definitions. Subscribe to my blog so you do not miss it! You might as well pick up my Key Performance Indicators PDF as well. It’s free!
 
I’m shooting to have it out in about a week.
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How would you guess the weight of this pumpkin?]]></title><description><![CDATA[
To confuse them is to literally confuse a thoughtful response with failing to respond.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/wisdom-of-crowds</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/wisdom-of-crowds</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>James offers a smart estimate based on the height and circumference of the pumpkin. Sean thinks he has an idea based on the load capacity of the truck that’s carrying it. I am tempted to google the answer by finding the pumpkin at a past event. I don’t, but only because I feel pretty confident. I can estimate the weight. I don’t need to guess. The officiator, Ryan, accepts my guess: “the average of all guesses.”

After the submission deadline passes I find out I am not in the winners circle because Ryan forgot to calculate my answer. “Let me add you in.” He says, “But it is going to be high. There were a some really high guesses.” I wait for him to calculate the average.

 

## “oh, Crap.”

At this point I know I’ve placed because Ryan says, “oh, crap.” The winners have already been chosen and I’ve bumped one out of the circle. The problem, Ryan already told him he won! I estimated the weight to within 10 lbs of the true weight!*

 

## How to Guess the Weight of any Pumpkin.

In 1907, Sir Francis Galton asked villagers to guess the weight of an ox. None of them guessed correctly. When Galton averaged their guesses, he arrived at a near perfect estimate. This is the classic example of the “wisdom of crowds”, or collective intelligence. More recently, the show, Brain Games, demonstrates how to guess the number of gumballs:

guess the number of gumballs

Pumpkin. Ox. Or gumballs in a machine. The wisdom of crowds has it’s moments. Each person’s perspective holds true information plus some degree of error. The individual errors of each guess get rounded out; they offset each other. Whats left? An estimate of the truth. Everyone getting it wrong, gets it right. It’s the diversity of eccentric perspectives that makes it work!  If we were to plot the answers on a graph you might assume the scatter-plot forms a bell curve: i.e. a lot of people guess close to the right answer. Not necessarily (See below). For sure, it’s not required to. The average is also not popular opinion, that is the mode. In this case the average is the shared consensus we get when we honor our differences.



## A Caveat: Averages Make for Poor KPIs.
It would be a mistake to rely on an average as a KPI. To benefit from the “[wisdom of crowds](https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0385721706/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=smarexceshor-20&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;creativeASIN=0385721706&amp;linkId=4803c6cf0b0092caaabf3bf7286b6a68
)” we need to meet certain [requirements](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wisdom_of_Crowds#Four_elements_required_to_form_a_wise_crowd). These requirements are not likely to exist in the context of an SOP. When you use an average as a KPI you are assuming that  it is representative of the whole, and it isn’t.

I often cringe when I see averages. I’ve been working on a resource to help teams create better measurements. I’ve looked and haven’t found one.  The options that I see lack either sophistication or practicality. I haven’t found a resource with both. I’m creating a resource that will (1) show you how to think correctly about KPIs and (2) how to do it in Excel. I invite you to check out what I am doing. Sign up on my email list for updates.

*Ryan &amp; [Hee Haw Farms](http://www.heehawfarms.com/) were good sports. We all won passes. My family saw [the giant pumpkin drop](http://www.heehawfarms.com/activities/giant-pumpkin-drop).
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Excel Shortcuts to Clean, Trim, and other useful formulas to Cleaning up data.]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Did you know what three Excel shortcuts save the most time? A: Cut, copy, paste. 
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/excel-shortcuts-clean-trim</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/excel-shortcuts-clean-trim</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
## Excel Shortcuts to Clean, Trim, and other useful formulas to Cleaning up data.

When working with data it is often necessary to ‘clean’ the data first so that you can work with it.  Often formatting is distracting or inconsistent, there may be extra spaces between words and on occasion there may be special characters that are not visible but, get in the way of working with data. Sometimes data is not in a format that you can use. This data needs to be prepped for use. Sometimes this is called data processing; we refer to it polishing data. Two common formulas for cleaning data include:

- clean()  Removes special characters from your cell values. 

- trim()  Removes extra spaces between words and at the ends of your cell value.

This video goes into how to use these two functions.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Excel Shortcuts to Cut, Copy, Paste, & Paste Values.]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Did you know what three Excel shortcuts save the most time? A: Cut, copy, paste. 
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/excel-shortcuts-insert-more-than-one-row-at-a-time</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/excel-shortcuts-insert-more-than-one-row-at-a-time</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
## How to Quickly Insert multiple blank rows or columns in Excel.

To quickly insert multiple rows in Excel it makes more sense to use a mouse shortcut. You can insert multiple blank rows all at once with the following steps:

Step 1: Select the number of rows you want to insert.

Step 2: Right click the selected rows, and choose the Insert item in the context menu, see this video demonstration below:

Alternatively, you can insert one row (right click and select ‘insert’) and then press F4 as many times as you need. This works when you are too lazy to count rows.

## Did you know there are only a handful of tools that differentiate an excel expert from an intermediate user?

Yesterday my good friend said, “Anytime someone says they are an excel expert I know they don’t know anything.” I know where he is coming from. I have the same bias. As I learn a new tool in Excel I realize how much more there is to learn. But you don’t have to know how to use every tool to be an expert. When it comes to Excel, it really is possible to become an expert in a short amount of time because there are only about a half dozen areas where people get stuck, bottlenecks. Manipulating data is one area where cut, copy, and paste is just a portion. If you would like to access my (Rho Lall’s) full mind-map,  Become An Excel Expert, it covers all five areas. Just follow this link to my become an excel expert mind-map.

</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The internet prior to 1984]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Do you remember what that is called?
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/internet-before-1994</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/internet-before-1994</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2012 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Do you remember what that is called?

I remeber having those . . . and  . . . these,

![internet prior to 1994](./media/content/internet_1994.png)

</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Murder: Crime Displacement over Time and Space]]></title><description><![CDATA[
It is a romantic suggestion that a neighborhood will come together in tragedy, albeit temporarily.  However, anecdotal evidence does suggest that under such circumstances the criminal element will lay low and bide its time until the heightened level of caution and police presence subsides.  While this makes intuitive sense, is there evidence to support such a conclusion?
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/crime-displacement-over-time-and-space</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/crime-displacement-over-time-and-space</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
In May of 2004 a coordinated search of Inwood Hills Park ended when police discovered the badly decomposed remains of Sarah Fox.  Fox had disappeared days before, shortly after she left her apartment for an afternoon jog.  In the days that followed, the neighborhood experienced a heightened level of caution, police presence in the area increased and media and news organizations held a constant vigil across the street from Fox’s apartment complex. It is a romantic suggestion that a neighborhood will come together in tragedy, albeit temporarily.  However, anecdotal evidence does suggest that under such circumstances the criminal element will lay low and bide its time until the heightened level of caution and police presence subsides.  While this makes intuitive sense, is there evidence to support such a conclusion?  This paper is the result of simple question: in the short term, is a neighborhood safer after a murder?  Is there a causal relationship between murder and common street crime?

The literature suggests two theories on criminal behavior: contagion effect and displacement effect.  These effects provide a theoretical explanation as to why the traditional choice model of constrained optimization does not fully explain the observable variability in crime across space and time.  Under the constrained optimization model, criminals seek to maximize utility given a fixed constraint such as civil and criminal penalties.  Criminals will commit crimes when the expected benefits exceed the expected costs (Becker 1968). Chang indicates that criminals look for easy opportunities; burglars prefer homes, large commercial buildings, or buildings with alleyway access over more closely guarded buildings (2011). This suggests that criminals consider costs and benefits and look to optimize benefits under risk constraints.  However, neighborhood demographics alone do not account for the variability in crime across time and space. Glaeser states, “Positive covariance across agents’ decisions about crime is the only explanation for variance in crime rates higher than the variance predicted by differences in local conditions” (Glaeser 1996, 508).  The gap in explanatory power suggest that there are other significant forces beyond the traditional choice model.

Narayan, Nielsen, and Smyth’s work in the American Journal of Economics and Sociology indicates that there is a natural rate of crime that remains impervious to efforts to reduce crime rate in the long-run (2010). They call short-run variations from the long-run natural crime rate structural breaks.  Contagion and displacement effects are the principal sources of these deviations from the natural rate of crime in a given time and space.

Glaeser explains contagion theory as peers’ influence overshadowing the criminal’s innate disposition towards crime (1996). Peers influence a criminal’s preferences by reducing stigma or increasing social distinction. Through misinformation, peers distort a criminal’s frame of reference and understanding of the costs and benefits. Peers can relax constraints by assisting directly or providing some technology or special knowledge that decreases a criminal’s likelihood of being caught (Glaeser 1996). Contagion effects involve copycats and retaliatory crimes as well (Jacob 2007). When peers’ actions influence a criminal’s decision to act there is a multiplier effect; the neighborhood’s actual crime rate will increase beyond a predicted crime rate based solely on neighborhood demographics (Glaeser 1996).

Hesseling explains the displacement effect as an inelastic demand for crime: “offenders are flexible and can commit a variety of crimes; and the opportunity structure offers unlimited alternative targets” (Hesseling 1994, 220). Criminals will not abandon their criminal pursuit at infinitum when encountering an obstacle. Instead, they will seek another opportunity to commit a crime with a similar cost benefit analysis. Criminals alter their course of action in order to bypass “conditions unfavorable to the offender’s usual mode of operating” (Gabor 1990, 66 in Harding 1994). The crime is displaced to “other times, places, methods, targets or offense” (Repetto 1976 in Hesseling 1994, 198). Individuals have a specific desired outcome for committing a crime. Hesseling’s detailed overview of related literature supports the rational choice aspect of displacement theory.

Displacement can occur in a variety of ways making it difficult to measure and account for. Researchers examine the effect case by case in discussions about motivations and strategy with criminals or in measuring the statistical impact of a policy on crime reduction in a myriad of times and venues (Hesseling 1994). We employ the later methodology.

We assume that murder, our quasi-experimental treatment, is particularly newsworthy and sufficiently shocking for the neighborhood to react strongly. We predict that we should see an increase in police presence and general wariness among the local population. Inhabitants of the neighborhood will be more cautious and act so as to limit their vulnerabilities for becoming victims themselves. We expect this to have a negative effect on street crime. Criminals will restrain illicit activities until such time where the community and police force are not as alert. Criminals will displace crime into a different area or into a later time period. Murder should have a displacement effect on street crime in the short run.  

Oakland, the eighth largest city in California, is rife with crime. It is home to 390,724 people. Since 2007, there have been 874 murders, and 105,589 crimes committed, that is a crime for every four people. Given the high level of crime, it will be the source for our experiment.

The Oakland Crimespotting project compiles data on crimes from the City of Oakland’s CrimeWatch program which publicizes data from daily police reports. Crimespotting combines crime data and mapping in a convenient matter.  The data comes in a format with a single observation for each crime.  Each observation includes variables that identify the type of crime, location (longitude and latitude), and date when it occurred.  This data is current to the day, and it extends back through 2007. Crimespotting divides the data into thirteen categories: aggravated assault, murder, robbery, simple assault, disturbing the peace, narcotics, alcohol, prostitution, theft, vehicle theft, vandalism, burglary, and arson.  However, Crimespotting does not include data on weather conditions.  It is plausible that weather would influence crime.  Weather Underground offers historic data on the temperature and level of precipitation.

We aggregate the data because is too granular to work with in its raw state.  We sum the observations across zip codes and by date in order to obtain the total amount of crime for each day in each zip code (or neighborhood). We identify the dates of all murders and subsequently calculate the average amount of crime that occurs in the following week as well as for the week prior.  

We apply the same process for those neighborhoods that did not experience a murder in order to determine the crime rates in neighborhoods in which a murder did not occur. From this second group we select neighborhoods that are comparable in terms of their crime rates. In order to ensure that we match similar neighborhoods, we restrict the data to a range of two standard deviations from the mean number of crimes committed per day in a zip code with a murder. To determine these cutoff points, we identify the average neighborhood crime rate conditional on there being a murder, which is 7.5.  The lowest average crime rate was 2.8, and the highest was 15 crimes a day. We drop from our data those neighborhood time period combinations that have an average of fewer than 4.5 crimes a day and neighborhoods that have greater than, on average, 10.5 crimes a day. Such a restriction would eliminate neighborhoods on both ends of the crime spectrum. After all, murders in an extremely crime ridden area would likely not illicit the same dramatic response as murders in a more moderate neighborhood. Additionally, neighborhoods with historically low crime rates will not boast substantial enough crime rates to generate any responsible understanding of causal effects.

Our model uses two specifications to determine if street crime in Oakland has any sensitivity to murder:  before and after, and difference in difference.  Both the before and after and difference in difference specifications assume the counter-factual that crime rate will remain unchanged in the absence of a murder in the area in which a murder took place.  The difference in difference also assumes that the general crime-rates in both the treatment and non treatment areas are similar; the standard errors for both groups are statistically equivalent.  If the standard errors are different or if we detect contagion or displacement effects the specification is unsubstantionable.  We check these assumptions with an OLS specification with a lagged variable for when a murder occurs to see its effect on crime.

Preliminarily, we employ the before and after approach and look at only the neighborhoods that have murders.  We compare the crime rates before and after each murder.  This is a basic comparison of the average crime rates in the time periods before and after each murder. For this specification we assume that the crime rate in the post-treatment period is equal to the pre-treatment crime rate in the absence of a murder.  Without any shocks or intervening variables, crime rate should maintain its historical trend.  Thus, any change in the crime rate is attributable to the murder.

The natural extension of the before and after analysis is to include a control group for comparison.  The difference in difference specification allows us to do this.  We can compare the average crime rates before and after each murder.  We can also compare crime rates between  neighborhoods with murders and those without.  To complete a difference in difference specification we use two dummy variables that partition the sample into four groups.  The first dummy variable, treatment, partitions the sample in two halves based on their treatment status.  The second dummy variable, post, partitions the halves in quarters based on the time period.

We identify neighborhoods in Oakland that match in terms of crime rates and geographic size. We assume that demographic and macroeconomics variables (economic prosperity, level of unemployment, ethnicity, and association with a given crime group) are held constant across the two neighborhoods during the week long intervals before and after a murder. This is a necessary evil given the lack of data available on such indicators on a scale smaller than the city level.

We control for several variables.  We assume that crime rates vary based on the date and whether school is on holiday; so, we control for the date a crime was committed. Additionally, we control for the particular neighborhood (zip code). Existing literature indicates that crime rates are highly correlated to drug use. We generate a dummy variable for the first seven days after the first of the month. Government distributes entitlements on the first of the month; therefore, drug addicts will likely spend this disposable income on drugs and spend the next couple of days in a drug induced stupor. Crime should decrease over that short time period. We control for weather, temperature, and precipitation.  It is likely that on hot, dry days crime will increase. However, on cooler or rainy days criminals are more likely to stay of the streets.

Our results indicate that there is no causal relationship between murder and street crimes. (* Indicates a value that is not statistically significant.) Graph 1 depicts the average daily crime rate leading up to and after 40 murders in our sample. The red vertical line is day the murders happen. The black line represents total crime and the other lines represent corresponding crime categories: red for violent crime, green for crimes relating to property, and blue for miscellaneous crimes. This is visual evidence that murder does not have a causal effect on crime.

The before and after approach reveals that there is not sufficient preliminary evidence to support our hypothesis. A murder in Oakland decreases other street crimes by one twentieth of a crime, .05*. The average week in an Oakland neighborhood sees 8.58 crimes a day.  During the week following a murder, in a given neighborhood street crime drops to 8.53* crimes a day.

The difference in difference specification does not provide evidence to support our hypothesis.  Murder has a coefficient of 1.3757 (.3008) suggesting that murder, as a treatment, actually is positively correlated with crime rates. A post-treatment time frame variable indicates, on contrast a slightly negative correlation with crime rates. The interaction term between these two variables, and a more holistic view of the difference in difference effect, is .1805* (.4250). While ever so slightly positive, this correlation is statistically insignificant with a relatively large standard error and a particularly small t-statistic (.425). Indeed, only the treatment and the temperature control have a standard error large enough to prove significant (4.574 and 5.280 respectively).

We note that precipitation, first of the month dummy, and multiples homicides variables boarder on statistical significance. With a t-statistic of -1.806 and a coefficient of -.1802, multiple murders (or a weighted impact of murder) has a negative correlation to crime. On a rainy day, one can expect a small blimp in crime rates. Additionally, with a coefficient of .5362 (.2781), the first of the month dummy variable is positively correlated to crime rates. T-statistics less than 2 render the results dubious. See Table 1 for more details.

###1 Table
&lt;br/&gt;


| Feature          	| Estimated Coefficient 	| Standard Error 	| T-value 	|
|------------------	|-----------------------	|----------------	|---------	|
| Murder           	| 1.375720              	| 0.300775       	| 4.574   	|
| Post             	| 0.032416              	| 0.301222       	| 0.108   	|
| MurderPost       	| 0.180461              	| 0.425041       	| 0.425   	|
| Temperature      	| 0.076992              	| 0.014583       	| 5.280   	|
| Precipitation    	| 0.010179              	| 0.005694       	| 1.788   	|
| First Week       	| 0.526237              	| 0.278059       	| 1.893   	|
| Multiple Murders 	| -0.180162             	| 0.099745       	| -1.806  	|

&lt;br/&gt;

To check for the robustness of our model, we replace murder with another high profile crime: arson. Like murder, arson is positively correlated to high rates of crime with a coefficient of 3.598. When interacting with the after treatment variable, arson appears to have a very slight negative effect on crime rates (-.049)*.

 

Previously, we looked at crime as a whole; however, to analyse subtle effects we look at how murder impacts categories of crime. Murder is strongly correlated with violent crimes; however, it is more weakly correlated with property crimes and what we refer to as miscellaneous crimes: disturbing the peace, prostitution, alcohol, and narcotics. The difference in differences mechanism reveals a similar trend, albeit a statistically insignificant one. Murder has a small negative effect on future instances of miscellaneous and violent crimes; however, there was a very small positive correlation with property crimes. See Table 2 for specific figures.

### Tabe 2
&lt;br/&gt;


| Types of crime 	| Estimated Coefficient of Treatment 	| Estimated Coefficient of Post 	| Estimated Coefficient of TreatmentPost 	|
|----------------	|------------------------------------	|-------------------------------	|----------------------------------------	|
| Violent        	| 1.315547&lt;br/&gt;(0.125213)                	| 0.030097*&lt;br/&gt;(0.125213)          	| -0.137175*&lt;br/&gt;(0.176955)           	|
| Property       	| 0.865536&lt;br/&gt;(0.154010)                	| 0.041623*&lt;br/&gt;(0.154010)          	| 0.170580*&lt;br/&gt;(0.217631)            	|
| Miscellaneous  	| 0.809375&lt;br/&gt;(0.095011)                	| 0.018875*&lt;br/&gt;(0.094612)          	| -0.011316*&lt;br/&gt;(0.133721)                  	|

&lt;br/&gt;

If our hypothesis were to hold, murder should have a more dramatic effect on crime rates during the short term (a two day time frame) compared to a long term (a 30 day time frame). However, both time frames yield similar results -.3686* and -.30036* respectively. While, the long term effect is slightly smaller, the difference is insignificant. However, the t-values are -.626 and -.738 respectively.

Our initial question has also gone unanswered due to lack of evidence.  Our simple question was not adequate to illuminate such a complex issue.  We found that murder is strongly correlated with crime, however, our results on the effects of murder on post-murder crime rates proved statistically insignificant and extremely small. The process was valuable in helping us form better ideas about pursuing this area of study.

Fundamentally, we need to ask a different question.  We learned that crime is a complex social issue with a lot of variability.  Looking at a short time frame was not beneficial in reducing the impact of this variability.  In light of our research into contagion and displacement effects, had we more time we would revisit our empirical specification.  To assume away contagion and displacement effects on the basis that they were unobserved is ill-advised. To rectify this we would want to explore more substantial time elements beyond the simple time frame of before and after.  Similarly, we would want to look at more subtle geographic variations in crime rates. This would preclude the difference in difference model in favor of another option.  

Similarly, the lack of controls for neighborhood demographic data concerns us. We cannot find such data at the neighborhood level.  We could have created a variable, day, that counts the days in relation to their relative position to a murder, similar to Graph 1.  We could then use this variable in a fixed effect specification.  Additionally, to test more effectively for geographic displacement, we would want to be able to look at geographic units smaller than the zip code level. However, with the data and tools accessible to us, this was impossible.  Finally, we should expand the study to include a broader range of cities. Any result based solely on Oakland data is not generalizable to the nation or criminology as a whole.

Our theoretical framework is based on the assumption that murder is a sufficiently heinous crime to illicit a strong response to it and therefore to induce a displacement effect in the short run. Ultimately, however, our experiment suggests that murder does not have a strong displacement effect. It simultaneously suggests that murder does not induce a contagion effect.
 

### Bibliography

Becker, Gary S. 1968. “Crime and Punishment: An Economic Approach.” Journal of Political Economy 76:169–217.

Chang, Dongkuk. 2011. “Social Crimes or Spatial Crime? Exploring the Effects of Social, Economical, and Spatial Factors on Burglary Rates.” Environment &amp; Behavior 43, no. 1: 26-52.

Gabor, T. 1990. “Crime Displacement and Situational Prevention: Toward the Development of Some Principles.” Canadian Journal of Criminology 32: 41-73.

Glaeser, Edward L., Bruce Sacerdote, and José A. Scheinkman. 1996. “Crime and Social Interactions” The Quarterly Journal of Economics 111, no. 2: 507-548.

Hesseling, René B.P. 1994. “Displacement: A Review of the Empirical Literature.” Research and Documentation Centre, Ministry of Justice, The Netherlands. http://www.popcenter.org/library/crimeprevention/volume_03/07_hesseling.pdf (accessed 7 April 2011)

Jacob, Brian, Lars Lefgren, and Enrico Moretti. 2007. “The Dynamics of Criminal Behavior: Evidence from Weather Shocks.” Journal of Human Resources 42, no. 3: 489-537.

Narayan, Paresh Kumar, Ingrid Nielsen, and Russell Smyth. 2010. “Is There a Natural Rate of Crime?.” American Journal of Economics and Sociology 69, no. 2: 759-782.

Reppetto, Thomas A. 1976. “Crime Prevention and the Displacement Phenomenon.” Crime &amp; Delinquency 22:166-177.

Tompson, Lisa, and Michael Townsley. 2010. “(Looking) Back to the Future: Using Space–time Patterns to Better Predict the Location of Street Crime.” International Journal of Police Science &amp; Management 12, no. 1: 23-40.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Economics of Economics Blogs]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Attempts at controlling extreme risk should come with a warning, here be dragons.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/economics-of-economics-blogs</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/economics-of-economics-blogs</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
The Gist:  If you are a professor, the takeaway is that you want to have a department blog that you contribute to unless you are a prolific publisher with a horde of minions to do your bidding.

If you are a consumer of economic literature, you are not alone. Here is a list of econ blogs to start you off (google it).

Development Impact

Freakonomics.com

Chris Blattman

NYT’s Economix

Marginal Revolution

Paul Krugman

The Statistic: Blogging about a paper causes a large increase in the number of abstract views and downloads in the same month: an average impact of an extra 70-95 abstract views in the case of Aid Watch and Blattman, 135 for Economix, 300 for Mararginal Revolution, and 450-470 for Freakonomics and Krugman.

The Article: [The Economics of Economics Blogs](https://freakonomics.com/2011/08/the-economics-of-economics-blogs/):

Last week, the World Bank blog Development Impact wrote about the influence of economics blogs on downloads of research papers. It included Freakonomics.com, as well as 5 other blogs — Aid Watch, Chris Blattman, NYT’s Economix, Marginal Revolution, and Paul Krugman. Using stats from Research Papers in Economics, it found spikes after blogs cover a paper. For us, they found that when we blogged a paper, there was an additional 450-470 abstract views and downloads that month. Check out their cool graph:

![chart](./media/content/chart_economic_blogs.png)

(Courtesy of Berk Ozler and David McKenzie)

This is part of a series Development Impact is doing on economics blogs. Part Two is on whether a blog increases the blogger’s profile and whether that effects policy. Part Three, just posted on Sunday, measures the causal impact of econ blogs by “using a variety of data sources and empirical techniques, we feel we have provided quantitative evidence that economic blogs are doing more than just providing a new source of procrastination for writers and readers.”

So there you go, from the World Bank itself. Freakonomics.com, changing the world one abstract at a time.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Appropriate Use of Risk]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Attempts at controlling extreme risk should come with a warning, here be dragons.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/appropriate-use-of-risk</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/appropriate-use-of-risk</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
Medieval mapmakers often noted the risk of an unknown kind by the notation “here be dragons”. 
Attempts at controlling extreme risk should come with a similar warning. 
Just like the sailors of yesteryear, financial institutions will go into unknown territories and, just like the map makers of that era, modern risk modellers have [very little to say](https://voxeu.org/article/appropriate-use-risk-models-part-i). </content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Notes on Difference in Differences Estimation]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Before and After.  This is a basic comparison of means for the time periods before and after treatment.   For this specification we assume that Y in the post-treatment period is equal to Y in the pre-treatment period in the absence of treatment.  
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/counterfactual-analysis-2011</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/counterfactual-analysis-2011</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>

Difference in Difference Estimation:

Y = B0 + B1*Post + B2*Treatment + B3*Post*Treatment.

- Y, is the dependent variable we are interested in estimating.
- Post, is a binary dummy variable indicating whether an observation is in the post treatment period.
- Treatment, is a binary dummy variable indicating whether an received treatment or not.
- B3 is the estimator, the coefficient on Post*Treatment.

Before and After.  This is a basic comparison of means for the time periods before and after treatment.  For this specification we assume that Y in the post-treatment period is equal to Y in the pre-treatment period in the absence of treatment.  Thus, any change in the crime rate is attributable to the treatment.

Difference in Difference.  The natural extension of the before and after analysis is to include a control group for comparison.  The difference in difference specification allows us to do this.  We can compare Y as we did for the before and after analysis.  We can also compare Ys between treated and untreated groups.  To complete a difference in difference specification we use two dummy variables that partition the sample into four groups.  The first dummy variable, treatment, partitions the sample in two halves based on their treatment status.  The second dummy variable, post, partitions the halves in quarters based on the time period.  We then interact treatment and post (Post*Treatment); the coefficient on Post*Treatment estimates the statistical difference in Y.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A look At the Fundamental Premise of The Book of Mormon Musical (Old)]]></title><description><![CDATA[
I was interested in the churches role and influence in Africa so i looked up some numbers. Just the facts; no song and dance.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/book-of-mormon-musical-fundamental-premise-old</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/book-of-mormon-musical-fundamental-premise-old</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
The Book of Mormon Musical is about a Mormon missionary that is called to minister in Africa. 
He arrives in Africa and confronts realities of life for which he finds his dogma insufficient at best.

I was interested in the churches role and influence in Africa so i looked up some numbers. Just the facts; no song and dance.

## Number of Beneficiaries of Humanitarian Aid (2003 – 2010)
&lt;br/&gt;

| Immunizations (with other organizations)      || 42,465,500    |
| --------------------------------------------- |--| ----------- |
| Clean Water                                   ||  3,953,601    |
| Vision Care                                   ||  3,953,601    |
| Neonatal Resuscitation Training               ||     53,130    |
| Wheelchairs                                   ||     37,853    |
| Food Production/Nutrition                     ||      1,000    |
| Other health initiatives total                ||        100    |
| **Total beneficiaries**                       || **46,644,893** |

## Africa Church Statistics
&lt;br/&gt;

| Converts (1/1/10 – 9/30/10)    || 16,198   |
| --------------------------------------------- |--| ----------- |
| Stakes and Districts  || 104   |
| Wards and Branches  || 961 |
| Missions   || 18   |
| Temples   || 3  |
| **Total Church Membership**                       ||     **318,947**   |
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Research Methodology for a Literature Review]]></title><description><![CDATA[
This is my methodology / algorithm for completing a literature review on any given topic.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/literature-review</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/literature-review</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
This is my methodology / algorithm for completing a literature review on any given topic.

- I start with what is on Google Videos.
- I follow up with a visit to Wikipedia and a Google Search; it is a good idea to include “methodology” or “research methodology” in your search.
- Check out the ‘Annual Reviews’ Database at your local library website.
- Finally I gather articles from the the appropriate EBSCO hosted Journals and other sources.

I found the following video was helpful:

How to Conduct a Literature Review by Barton Poulson

[![How to Conduct a Literature Review by Barton Poulson](https://img.youtube.com/vi/O3oSQljU46U/hqdefault.jpg)](https://youtu.be/O3oSQljU46U)

[Caveat: My process is tailored to my learning preferences (auditory / kinesthetic).]</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What is the beta on environmental litigation when you regress risk premium on company metrics?]]></title><description><![CDATA[
If we develop a company specific factor model of the risk premium that includes these variables among other significant variables, we should be able to identify company specific traits with explanatory power.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/beta-on-risk</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/beta-on-risk</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
The CAPM is an elementary model of the risk premium or return a stock earns above a risk free rate. It measures the stock’s performance relative to a benchmark such as the S&amp;amp;P 500 or the Russell 2000. This model is used to calculate a stocks Beta. A stock with a Beta of one moves in lock step with the market. A stock with a Beta of 1.6 or more is a lot more volatile. A stock with a negative Beta is counter-cyclical, meaning that it moves opposite to the market.

A factor model builds on the CAPM. A factor model may look at other macroeconomics factors such as inflation, the interest rate and other macroeconomic indicators. A company specific factor model would look at company specific factors such as: earnings, P/E, ROE, ROA, ROIC.** If we develop a company specific factor model of the risk premium that includes these variables among other significant variables, we should be able to identify company specific traits with explanatory power.

Controlling for these variables we could then look at the effect of environmental litigation on a company’s risk premium, in essence the return to its shareholders. This information would be interesting in determining if litigation serves as a deterrent or if it is just a nuisance. Is the presence of litigation enough to provide an incentive for firms to correct actions?

A current example would be Transocean, the owner of the Deepwater Horizon which was at the heart of the BP oil spill last year. TransOcean’s stock price dropped in the days following the BP oil spill, although, BP and its minority partner assumed the risk of the deep water operation. RIG was a contractor. It would be interesting to see how litigation affects TransOcean’s returns to its shareholders and how that plays out in the aftermath of the BP oil spill.

- P/E: Price to earnings.
- ROE: Return on equity.
- ROA: Return on assets.
- ROIC: Return on invested capital</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Wordle]]></title><description><![CDATA[
This site will take any document (blog) and reduce it to it’s key themes.  I can think of several interesting applications for introspection and pre-reading . . . 
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/wordle</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/wordle</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2010 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>www.wordle.net

I have a new research toy.  This site will take any document (blog) and reduce it to it’s key themes.  I can think of several interesting applications for introspection and pre-reading documents.

This image is a wordle of my blog.  It is interesting that [“Bloomberg var”](https://web.archive.org/web/20150907220213/http://assume-wisely.blogspot.com/2011/02/financial-risk-analysis-from-bloomberg.html) (and any other financial term) doesn’t even make the list.

I think I might try this on a few of the academic articles I read to see what comes out of it.  Like I said, many interesting applications.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Naked Economics Chapter 13 Summary: development Economics]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Naked Economics Chapter 13 Summary: Boiled down to a simple idea, we can split that atom, land on the moon, decode the human genome, yet two billion people live on less than $2 a day. Their economies have failed them.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-13-summary</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-13-summary</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
## DEVELOPMENT ECONOMICS: Governments can sometimes improve market outcomes.

Why does half the world’s population live on less than $2 a day?  In Chapter 12, Wheelan’s thesis is an answer to this question; “their economies have failed them.”  He goes on to show “that government can sometimes improve market outcomes (Mankiw 7)”, and conversely when economies fail their people so do governments.  Wheelan draws several more conclusions, based on his second thesis.

The first, “Excessive regulation goes hand in glove with corruption (p. 211).”  Harvard economist Robert Barro has found that government consumption, excluding education and defense, is negatively correlated with per capita GDP, (p. 211).  A less benign corollary is that excessive regulation allows for government officers the opportunity to take bribes from those seeking a way around the regulation. Hernando De Soto’s documented study of opening a business in Peru revealed that it was impossible to start a business legally without bribes. The process was exhaustive and posed a significant barrier to entry in the Market. (p. 211)  Governments interference stifles growth in this case.

His second conclusion, informal property rights render real estate property less productive, (p. 210).  This means that real property cannot be collateralized.  This stifles growth.  The Economist tells such a story of a Malawian business that cannot raise capital to grow its business despite their “ownership” of a home that would cover the cost.  De Soto reports that such situations result in $9 trillion in uncollateralized real property. (p. 210)  If government would formalize property rights then citizens would be able to collateralize real property stimulating their economies.  Drawing a parallel between these two conclusions shows that government must balance its role.

 

## SUPPORT FOR FORMAL PROPERTY RIGHTS

            De Soto’s argument support reform for formalized property rights.  Wheelan doesn’t directly discuss why this issue persists.  There must be reasons, possibly such as protectionist logic or politics.  At the heart of the issue could be that if property is leveraged to incur debt it would be possible for foreign micro lenders to foreclose on the property in the case of default.  Clearly foreign investors would have an advantage.  Even with formal property rights land still belongs to government.  To illustrate lets assume that an owner of land in the US stops paying taxes on that land.  The property will be seized.  Data that would flesh this out would be valuable to De Soto.  Show the benefits through an analysis comparing the benefit to the risk.  Fundamentally the benefit must outweigh the risk because real property cannot be exported to another country. 

CHALLENGING GDP AS A MEASURE OF OUR COLLECTIVE WELL-BEING

GDP is a good measure of a countries standard of living because it directly measures production.  A country’s standard of living depends on its production, Mankiw 8.  GDP like any statistic has its limits; Wheelan sympathizes with other social scientists, he illustrates GDP’s shortcomings. He explains alternatives to the use of GDP as a measure of our standard of living such as, “Bennett’s index of leading cultural indicators”, the United Nation’s “Human development index” and Miringhoff’s “social health index” (p. 155). He subtly points out that any measure is a statistic and has limitations. He doesn’t however go on to explain that GDP is an actionable statistic as opposed to these other indexes. He could highlight the direct, causal, relationship between production and standard of living. Allso these other measures are direct or causal. They measure symptoms not causes.

## Notes

We can split that atom, land on the moon, decode the human genome, yet two billion people live on less than $2 a day. Their economies have failed them.
Creating wealth is a process of taking inputs, including human talent, and producing things of value.
Why can Pakistan build nuclear weapons but is unable to conduct immunization programs against measles?
What does a government need for effective institutions?
Rule of law. Law enforcement, courts, infrastructure, a government capable of collecting taxes, and a healthy respect for these institutions. 
Corruption is a cancer that misallocates resources, stifles innovation, and discourages foreign investment. 
There is a clear and causal relationship between better governance and better development outcomes such as higher per-capita income, lower infant mortality, and higher literacy.
Property Rights. 
Dead Capital: DEF
Human Capital Trap
Dutch Disease
Explain how poor countries are like poor people.  What can the developed world do to provide more effective aid for these countries?
Books:
Hardworking Mr. Zimba, a 25-year-old man in Malawi
Poor: $40 in 2000. Today, the Malawian entire annual economic output is about $12 billion; half the size of Vermont

Africa
United Republic of Tanzania, Mozambique, Zimbabwe, Zambia, Democratic Republic of the Congo, Malawi
Malawi
								
Gross Domestic Product - GDP US$ 5.727 billion (2009 estimate)
								
GDP (Purchasing Power Parity) 14.68 billion of International dollars (2010 estimate )
								
Real GDP growth
								
2000 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 0.8% -4.1% 1.7% 5.5% 5.5% 2.6% 7.7% 5.8% 2008 2009 2010* 2011* 2012**
8.8% 9% 6.5% 5.5% 4.3%
								
*Estimate **Forecast
								
GDP per capita - current prices US$ 344 (2009 estimate)
								
GDP per capita - PPP $883 International Dollars (2009 estimate)
							
South Korea
								
Gross Domestic Product - GDP US$ 1.164 trillion (2010 estimate) GDP(Purchasing Power Parity) 1.63 trillion of International
								
dollars (2010 estimate )
								
Real GDP growth
								
2000 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 8.8% 4% 7.2% 2.8% 4.6% 4% 5.2% 5.1% 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012
								
2.3% 0.3% 6.3% 3.6% 3.5%
GDP per capita - current prices US$ 23,680 (2010 estimate) GDP per capita - PPP $33,172International Dollars (2010 estimate)
								
Source:
								
http://www.gfmag.com/gdp-data-country-reports/241-south-korea- gdp-country-report.html
							
 In Malawi, 30% of the young children are malnourished; 2/10 will die before their 5th birthday

We can split the atom, land on the moon, decode the human genome, yet 2B people live on less than $2/day, 1B are hungry
Their economies have failed them
Creating wealth is a process of taking inputs, including human talent, and producing things of value
Poor countries are not organized to do that

Pakistan; busy, dynamic private economy, yet most are illiterate, ill housed and ill fed

They can build nuclear weapons, but cannot conduct an immunization program against the measles

 “Wonderful people. Terrible government” writes World Bank economist William Easterly

William Easterly

 An economist at the New York University, specializing in economic growth and foreign aid

 Published books: The Elusive Quest for Growth, and White Man’s Burden

 Distinguishes two types of foreign aid donors; the Planners and the Searchers

 Planners are top down approach; modern incarnations of colonialism
 Searchers look for bottom up solutions
 Easterly believes Searchers are more likely to succeed
 Every country has resources
 Bad news: Economists do not have a recipe for making poor countries rich.
 Some successes: the Asian tigers, China, India; yet no proven formula
 We know what makes rich countries rich; if we can catalog those successful policies, maybe we can have poor countries simply adopt them??
 The following are kinds of policies, and geographical endowments, that developmental economists believe make the difference between wealth and poverty

Effective Government Institutions
 Law, law enforcement, courts, infrastructure, and a government capable of collecting taxes – and a healthy respect of these institutions
 The tracks on which capitalism runs
 Corruption is a cancer that misallocates resources, stifles innovation, and discourages foreign investment
 Economists studied how the economic success of developing countries were affected by the quality of the institutions colonizers had left behind
 If it was hospitable, they built institutions; if not, it became an “extractive state”
 Of 64 colonies, 3⁄4 of the current wealth can be explained by the quality of their government institutions, which, in turn, can be explained by the original settlement pattern

 Good governance matters
									
 There is a clear and causal relationship between better governance and better development outcomes such as higher per capita incomes, lower infant mortality, and higher literacy

Property Rights
 There are many homes and businesses built on communal land or owned by the government or ignored.
 The crucial difference between the developed and the developing world? – owners have no legal title to the property; cannot rent it, subdivide it, sell it, or pass it on to family, or use it as collateral to raise capital
 In the developing world, informal property arrangements are very common, and should not be ignored (Peruvian economist Hernando de Soto)
 Value of property held but not legally owned by poor people: $9trillion – it’s “dead capital”
 Malawian couple wants to expand business, “owns” a house, but cannot borrow against it as they don’t have an official title
 Informal property rights are inadequate in a modern complex economy
 Property rights also frees us people’s time; less time spent defending their possessions
 People may leave their home, rather than setting up improvised businesses to protect their property
 Extending property rights gives the incentive to work
No Excessive Regulation
 Red tape; excessive bureaucracy
 Goes hand in hand with corruption
 Peruvian study: trying to set up a one person shop; group vowed not to pay bribes, asked for bribes 10 times, had to pay twice to avoid complete failure
 To set up a shop, it cost $1,231, or 31 times the monthly minimum wage
 Governments should limit spending; Barro’s study found government consumption, excluding education and defense, was NEGATIVELY correlated with GDP per capita growth
 Asian tigers government spending during growth was in the range of 20% of GDP
 High tax rates applied unevenly distort the economy; low, simple and easy to collect may improve government revenue
South Korea – Government consumption expenditures as % of GDP from 1967-2012, with future trend line,
from tradingeconomics.com
The Netherlands - Government consumption expenditures as % of GDP from 1967-2012, with future trend line
Human Capital
 This makes individuals productive, and productivity determines our standard of living
 Countries with persistent growth have had large increases in education and training of labor forces
 Education improves public health
 Associated with lower rates of infant mortality
 Facilitates the adoption of superior technologies (may borrow innovations)
 They don’t have to invent the computer, just learn how to use it
 The problem: skilled workers need other skilled workers to succeed
 IE. A surgeon needs trained nurses, anesthesiologists, firms that sell drugs and equipment, and a population that can afford it
 If there are few skilled workers, there is less incentive to invest in skills
	
 The skilled workers would leave: the “brain drain”
 If a country is skilled, it gets more skilled
 This happens in areas of America as well

Geography

 Two of the 30 rich countries lie between the Tropic of Cancer and the Tropic of Capricorn; Hong Kong and Singapore

 Tropical weather good for vacation, not so great for development

 High temperatures and heavy rain are bad for food production and conducive to the spread of disease

 Winter kills mosquitoes

 Tropics are filled with low-production farmers
Jeffrey Sachs’ two solutions:
1. More technological innovation aimed at the unique ecology of the tropics
								
-scientists go where the money is
								
-of 1,233 new drugs between 1975 and 1997, 13 were for tropical diseases; 9 of those done by the US for the war in Vietnam
								
-British PM suggested a $ prize
							
								
2. Opening the economies to the rest of the world
								
-get out of the trap of subsistence agriculture
								
-higher incomes in non-agricultural sectors
								
Openness to Trade
 Despite the benefits, many are still protectionist
 Trade barriers “incubate” industries and let them get strong enough to compete? –but they grow fat and lazy

 Open economies grow faster
 In a study of tariffs and other restrictions, closed countries grew at 0.7% per capita in the 1970s and 1980s, while open countries grew at 4.5% annually
 A closed economy opened up: 1% increase

 Is it lack of trade that makes them grow slowly, or other macroeconomic dysfunction?
 Does trade cause growth, or is the an activity of a growing economy?

 In a paper in American Economic Review by Jeffrey Frankel and David Romer, the authors say, “Yes. Trade causes growth; our results bolster the importance of trade and trade-promoting policies.”

 Need a different approach: we offer financial aid while blocking trade!
								
Responsible Fiscal and Monetary Policy

 Governments must spend to raise future productivity
	
 Large deficits crowd out private borrowers
 Chronic deficit spending signals future
										
problems
 Problems are compounded if governments borrow from abroad; foreign investors may lose confidence
 Don’t be like Argentina; from 1960 to 1994, the average inflation rate was 127%!!
Natural Resources Matter Less than You Think
 Israel GDP ($28,300) is far richer than its oil-rich neighbors, Saudi Arabia ($20,500) and Iran ($12,800)
\ Japan and Switzerland are resource-poor, but have done better than resource-rich Russia

 Angola is oil-rich, but is in a civil war, has the highest rate of civilians maimed by land mines, 1/3 children die before 5, and life expectancy is 42
 May actually be a detriment (?!)
 One study of 97 countries over two decades found of the top 18 fastest-growing nations, only 2 are rich with things that can be taken out of the ground. And growth was higher in those countries less endowed with natural resources. Why?
 Diverts resources from other industries like manufacturing and trade that is beneficial to long- term growth
 Vulnerable to wild swings in commodity prices
 Perverse effects of abundant natural resources known as “Dutch disease”
 The Netherlands found natural gas; natural gas exports drove up the value of the Guilder; life was difficult for exporters
 Gas revenues expanded social spending, raising employers’ social security contributions and production costs
 The discovery and exploitation of the natural gas distorted the economy and became a mixed blessing for a trading nation
 Finally, a country should use the resource income to make things better, but often don’t
 The president of Chad, upon receiving 4.5 million USD for oil revenues as a result of a new pipeline, spent it on weapons to fight rebels
 Education, public health, sanitation, immunizations, infrastructure; there a better ways to spend that money!
Democracy
 Is a check on egregious economic policies
 Amartya Sen, Harvard professor awarded the
Nobel Prize in Economics in 1998, studied famines
 Famines are not caused by crop failure, but by faulty political systems that prevent the market from correcting itself
 Minor agricultural disturbances became catastrophes because imports were not allowed, prices were not allowed to increase, farmers were not allowed to grow alternatives
 Politics interfered with the market’s ability to correct itself
Famines “never materialized in any country that is independent, that goes to elections regularly, that has opposition parties to voice criticism and that permits newspapers to report freely and question the wisdom of government policies without extensive censorship.”
								
-Amartya Sen
 Barro’s study found basic democracy is associated with higher economic growth, while advanced democracies suffer from slightly lower growth
 Consistent with what we know of interest groups
War is Bad
 Many poor countries are involved with armed conflicts
 3⁄4 of the world’s billion poorest are caught in a civil war or have recently been in one
 It’s hard to run a business or get an education while at war
 Natural resources can make things worse by financing the weapons
 Two ways to run a business in Somalia...
Woman Power

 Leaving one half of the land fallow
 Women do better, smarter things with
money
 More money on family nutrition, medicine, and housing; men spend it on alcohol and tobacco
 Development officials have learned to give cash to the woman; it will do much more good
Other Factors?
 Saving and investment rates, fertility rates, ethnic strife, colonial history, cultural factors...
 We know what’s good, then why is it so hard to get out of poverty?
 It’s one thing to say it, yet it’s another thing to DO it
 Effective government institutions are easier to build if the people are literate and educated
What should rich countries do to help the poor countries?
 Broad continuum of ideas
 Jeffrey Sachs says only capital from the
developed world will rescue them
 Spend more there, and you jump-start the development process
 Should undertake a comprehensive program to fight AIDS in Africa
 Invest for humanitarian reasons, AND the remote countries in turmoil become outposts of disorder to the rest of the world
 William Easterly says the development aid process is broken
 The peasant, his dying chickens, and the priest...
 Results are miserable at the micro level (mosquito nets become fishing nets or wedding veils) and macro (there is no evidence that current policy is working)
 We know free markets and good institutions are good, but we don’t know how to get from here to there
 Easterly says to stop helping poor countries, but focus on creating opportunities for individuals; small, context-centered projects with measurable benefits
 One study by Harvard Center for International Development found success rates can be explained by government policy
 Poor countries have bad habits; aid needs to be predicated by good policy	
 This will make aid more effective and provide incentives to governments to improve policy
It’s hard to turn away from the neediest case. From 2005 World Bank “Economic Growth in the 1990s: Learning from a decade of reform”:....no confident assertions, no policies to adopt; we need humility, policy diversity, for selective and modest reforms, and for experimentation. We need political will from rich country governments
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Naked Economics Chapter 10 Summary: The Federal Reserve]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Naked Economics Chapter 10 Summary: Boiled down to a simple idea, prices rise when the government prints too much money.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-10-summary</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-10-summary</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
## THE FEDERAL RESERVE: Prices rise when the government prints too much money.

Wheelan states point of fact that, “the Federal Reserve controls the money supply and therefore the credit tap for the country (p. 168).” He goes on to illustrate that “prices rise when the government prints too much money. (Mankiw 9)” He shows that if interest rates are too low then prices will rise but, GDP will ‘hit a wall’. (p. 170) This by definition is inflation. Wheelan draws several more conclusions, based on his second thesis.
The first, conclusion is that the great depression was the result of botched monetary policy. The Fed did not intervene as the money supply dried up. Money was hoarded; banks failed and people lost confidence in the banking system. This meant that there were no deposits available for loans. (p. 186) Nobel Prize winner, Robert Mundell, argued that monetary policy in the 1920s led to the great depression, and by extension, the Nazi revolution and World War II. The reason, central banks choose to adhere to gold standard in light of the falling price of gold. They should have chosen a policy emphasizing price stability.  Thus, the severity of the Great Depression could have been reduced.
His second conclusion, is that governments can cut their own debts by purposefully causing inflation. His argument is based on three logical points. First, governments often have large debt particularly when facing difficulties. Second, inflation favors debtors as it erodes that value of money they must pay back. Third, government controls the inflation rate. A small unstable government may deliberately cause inflation as a short term solution to buy time. (p. 182) This is not always the motivation. In 1980, US inflation climbed from 3%, in 1972, to 13.5%. Paul Volcker, lead the Fed to raise interest rates to 16%. This resulted in the recession of 1981-82, GDP shrunk by 3% and unemployment climbed to 10%. By 1983 inflation was back to 3%. (p. 172) So governments can intentionally cause inflation.


## CHALLENGING MOTIVATION FOR GOVERNMENT INSTIGATION OF INFLATION

Governments can cut their own debts by purposefully causing inflation for the reasons that Wheelan stated earlier. In Wheelan’s example the government printed money and paid its citizen’s with this money. In this respect Wheelan is right. However, what if this nation owes a debt to the IMF, the World Bank or the US? These loans are likely payable in U.S. dollars. In this instance inflating the local currency would not affect their responsibility to this debt. It is rare that a country could secure a loan payable in their own currency.  Data that would further support this would be a breakdown of government debt and it’s debtors.
In summary, this essay showed that governments can sometimes improve market outcomes (Mankiw 7), and that prices rise when the government prints too much money (Mankiw 9). It illustrated these principles using as examples: occupational licensing as encouraged by the teacher’s union, special interest group, since where we stand depends on where we sit, fouled monetary policy and the great depression, and Paul Volker’s anti inflationary monetary policy that lead to the recession of 1981. It looked at several conclusions that Wheelan drew, specifically: support for the special interests and challenging motivation for government instigation of inflation. It drew parallels between the motives for government to purposefully instigate inflation.
</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Naked Economics Chapter 9 Summary: Keeping Score]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Naked Economics Chapter 9 Summary: Boiled down to a simple idea, a country’s standard of living depends on its ability to produce.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-9-summary</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-9-summary</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
## KEEPING SCORE: A country’s standard of living depends on its ability to produce.

In Chapter 7, Wheelan’s thesis is that a country’s standard of living depends on its ability to produce goods and services.  This thesis is developed through an explanation and defense of GDP as an indicator of a nation’s prosperity.  He draws several conclusions to support this.

The first is that “any measure of economic progress depends on how you define progress. GDP just adds up the numbers.  All else equal, it is better for a nation to produce more goods and services than less (p. 155).”  He illustrates this with an example of how the real cost of goods decreases with time despite inflation raising the nominal cost.  He does this by measuring the real cost of living in time, the time it takes to earn the money equivalent to the price of the goods.  Thus, in 1900 it cost one hour and forty-one minutes of labor to purchase a pair of stockings. Today, it costs 18 minutes of labor to purchase a pair.

The second conclusion, GDP reflects more than just a number; “When GDP turns negative, the damage is real: jobs lost, businesses closed, productive capacity turned idle (p. 156).”  He illustrates the significance of India’s per capita GDP of $440.  In India there are 500,000 cases of leprosy.  The medication to cure leprosy only costs $3 and is provided for free by the World Health Organization.  However, their health care network is not structured to effectively diagnose and administer the medication.

 

## DEVELOPMENT ECONOMICS: Governments can sometimes improve market outcomes.

Why does half the world’s population live on less than $2 a day?  In Chapter 12, Wheelan’s thesis is an answer to this question; “their economies have failed them.”  He goes on to show “that government can sometimes improve market outcomes (Mankiw 7)”, and conversely when economies fail their people so do governments.  Wheelan draws several more conclusions, based on his second thesis.

The first, “Excessive regulation goes hand in glove with corruption (p. 211).”  Harvard economist Robert Barro has found that government consumption, excluding education and defense, is negatively correlated with per capita GDP, (p. 211).  A less benign corollary is that excessive regulation allows for government officers the opportunity to take bribes from those seeking a way around the regulation. Hernando De Soto’s documented study of opening a business in Peru revealed that it was impossible to start a business legally without bribes. The process was exhaustive and posed a significant barrier to entry in the Market. (p. 211)  Governments interference stifles growth in this case.

His second conclusion, informal property rights render real estate property less productive, (p. 210).  This means that real property cannot be collateralized.  This stifles growth.  The Economist tells such a story of a Malawian business that cannot raise capital to grow its business despite their “ownership” of a home that would cover the cost.  De Soto reports that such situations result in $9 trillion in uncollateralized real property. (p. 210)  If government would formalize property rights then citizens would be able to collateralize real property stimulating their economies.  Drawing a parallel between these two conclusions shows that government must balance its role.

 

## SUPPORT FOR FORMAL PROPERTY RIGHTS

            De Soto’s argument support reform for formalized property rights.  Wheelan doesn’t directly discuss why this issue persists.  There must be reasons, possibly such as protectionist logic or politics.  At the heart of the issue could be that if property is leveraged to incur debt it would be possible for foreign micro lenders to foreclose on the property in the case of default.  Clearly foreign investors would have an advantage.  Even with formal property rights land still belongs to government.  To illustrate lets assume that an owner of land in the US stops paying taxes on that land.  The property will be seized.  Data that would flesh this out would be valuable to De Soto.  Show the benefits through an analysis comparing the benefit to the risk.  Fundamentally the benefit must outweigh the risk because real property cannot be exported to another country. 

CHALLENGING GDP AS A MEASURE OF OUR COLLECTIVE WELL-BEING

GDP is a good measure of a countries standard of living because it directly measures production.  A country’s standard of living depends on its production, Mankiw 8.  GDP like any statistic has its limits; Wheelan sympathizes with other social scientists, he illustrates GDP’s shortcomings. He explains alternatives to the use of GDP as a measure of our standard of living such as, “Bennett’s index of leading cultural indicators”, the United Nation’s “Human development index” and Miringhoff’s “social health index” (p. 155). He subtly points out that any measure is a statistic and has limitations. He doesn’t however go on to explain that GDP is an actionable statistic as opposed to these other indexes. He could highlight the direct, causal, relationship between production and standard of living. Allso these other measures are direct or causal. They measure symptoms not causes.

In summary, this essay showed that governments can sometimes improve market outcomes and a country’s standard of living depends on its ability to produce goods and services. It illustrated these principles using as examples: the real cost of goods measured in time, India’s per capita GDP, De Soto’s research in real property and his study of corruption in government. It looked at several conclusions that Wheelan drew, specifically: GDP is a good measure of a countries standard of living because it directly measures production, GDP reflects more than just a number, excess government regulation leads to corruption, however, informal property rights hinder development.  It drew parallels between positive and negative government interaction.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Organized Interests. A definition from Naked Economics]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Organized Interests definition: a group of people or an organization seeking or receiving special advantages, typically through political lobbying. Another term is special interest.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-organized-interest-defined</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-organized-interest-defined</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
Organized Interests definition: a group of people or an organization seeking or receiving special advantages, typically through political lobbying. Another term is special interest.
Organized interests fuel a system that rewards self interested politicians who in turn cater to (the self interested) organized interest. 
The “economics of regulation” put simply is that the whole (large group) subsidizes the small group(s). 
You can read more to understand why in this [Naked Economics chapter 8 summary](/thoughts/naked-economics-chapter-8-summary).
 
Knowing the organized Interests definition is only a part of the story. All else equal, small, well organized groups are more successful in the political process. It is easier for the countless masses to pay a few extra cents in taxes to benefit a relative few. Those few are highly motivated to protect that benefit, whereas the general population is largely unaware. As a result, the democratic process will always favor small, well organized groups at the expense of large diffuse groups.
You can read more about Organized interests in this [Naked Economics chapter 8 summary](/thoughts/naked-economics-chapter-8-summary).


</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Ideas from Dead Economists: Milton Friedman]]></title><description><![CDATA[
According to, A Monetary History of the United States, ineffective monetary policy accompanied every severe recession and every significant inflationary period over the past and century
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/friedman</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/friedman</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
Friedman’s major contribution to the science of economics is his defense and argument for the quantity theory of money.  This theory argues that the quantity of money available determines the price level and the value of money.  It is a direct cause of inflation.  More money available in the market drives the price level up and the value of money down.  The devaluation of money is inflation. 

Friedman was a passionate debater who fought the Keynesian model.  Friedman had long held philosophical position that the true test of a theory is whether it correctly predicts events.  On this base Friedman argued two main points.  In an analogy, if an economy were a car government is usually a lousy driver.  In direct contrast to the Keynesian position, he argued the economy’s brake and accelerators have little to do a fiscal policy. 

He started an intellectual movement whose beliefs are encapsulated in monetarism.  Monetarism asserts that that changes made to the money supply are most material in the business cycle and in long run.  In the short run money can sway is not just prices but also economic activity. In the long run money supply only changes price.  Monetarists believe the economy’s accelerator is ‘a higher money supply’ and the economy’s brake is ‘lower money supply’.  According to, A Monetary History of the United States, ineffective monetary policy accompanied every severe recession and every significant inflationary period over the past and century (page 242).  The Federal Reserve is responsible for monetary policy.  The Fed affects the money supply through open market operations, the discount rate, and the reserve ratio.  They effectively hold the reigns of the economy.

He also worked on the idea of money velocity or how fast money changes hands in an economy.  The rate at which the money stock turns over each year is called the velocity of money.  Monetarists believe That velocity is stable, Keynesians see is unstable.  Historical data supports the monetarist position; as nominal GDP and the money supply increase velocity has stayed constant.</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Ideas from Dead Economists: Maynard Keynes]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Keynes provided an alternate school of thought and a solution. Keynes introduced the idea of marginal propensity to consume; a number that indicates a persons likeliness to spend an extra dollar. He used this to develop his solution, government spending on public resources so as to fill the gap left by consumption and investment.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/keynesian-economics</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/keynesian-economics</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
Keyenes most significant work, The General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money, .

Samuelson who introduced generations to Keynesian Economics said, it was, “a work of genius (p 214).”

It was very critical of his economic predecessors and colleagues. He directly attacks Say’s Law which states that producing goods provides workers with enough income for all goods to be purchased. Therefore resulting in zero surplus. If income was saved and not spent on goods then the savings would be utilized for business investment which would make up the difference. In the instance that investment didn’t make up the difference a recession would ensue but, the resulting drop in prices and wages would soon end it. This is the classical school of economics. Keynes did not believe that saving equaled investment. He argued that savers and investors do so for various reasons. He also argued that in a recession workers who are laid off are unable to save and businesses are reluctant to invest.

Keynes provided an alternate school of thought and a solution. Keynes introduced the idea of marginal propensity to consume; a number that indicates a persons likeliness to spend an extra dollar. He used this to develop a formula for his keynesian multiplier. His idea was that any increase or reduction in production will produce a multiplier effect that magnifies the change by a factor of the multiplier which is based on the aggregate MPC. His solution was for government to spend public resources so as to fill the gap left by consumption and investment.

He created an entirely separate school of thought. People who identify with this school are considered Keynesian. This theory is characterized by a belief that private economy may not reach full employment and that public spending by the government can fill the void. (p. 207)</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Naked Economics Chapter 2 Summary: Incentives Matter]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Naked Economics Chapter 2 Summary: Boiled down to a simple idea, be wary of what you wish for because it might not be what you want. Incentives matter but like a genie in a bottle they are problematic.
]]></description><link>https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-2-summary</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://assumewisely.com/thoughts/artificial-intelligence/naked-economics-chapter-2-summary</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2009 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>
30-53 Why you might be able to save your face by cutting off your nose (if you are a black rhino)

Theme - Misaligned incentives

53- how is it that a country can put a man on the moon and still have people sleeping on the street?
- Rocket Science vs drug addicts and 16 year old teens
- People seek to make themselves better off, however they may define that.
- Our best hope is to understand why we act the way we do, and plan accordingly.
- Programs, organizations, and systems work better when they get the incentives right.



31 - communal resources VS private property IE “rhino ranchers”
- Rats vs rhinos
- Free riders
- Incentives to hunt rhinos outnumber the disincentives

34- adam smith butcher quote
- Microsoft example
- Berlin wall, east german car company
- India, owned byt the state
	- North Korea

35- dependence on foreign oil &amp; CO2 emissions

36- Adverse Selection
- teacher salaries

36-37 Perverse incentives
- Law of unintended consequences
- Requiring car seats on planes might result in more injuries and deaths to children
Mexican smog

38- good use on incentives
- london
</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>